Today's דף daf *daf* is י"ז *Yod-Zayin*, we pick up with a
משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* on the bottom of י"ב עמוד ב' amud beis
*Yod-Bet Amud Bet*, we're continuing to move on with interesting scenarios about
מציאה *metziah*, we've gone from fighting over מציאה *metziah* to falling on
a מציאה *metziah* to who a מציאה *metziah* going to your yard
to if family members pick it up who owns it. And now
we're going to revisit something that we did glancingly a while ago
about finding a שטר חוב shtar chov *shtar chov*, a document of
debt, and who to return it to because obviously the question is
whether it's been paid up or not. So let's take a look.
מצא שטר shtar חוב *matza shtar chov*, so you find a document
of debt. It says ראובן *Reuven* borrowed a thousand dollars from שמעון
Shimon, *Shimon*, let's say שמעון *Shimon* borrowed a thousand from ראובן *Reuven*.
אם יש בהן אחריות נכסים achrayut nechasim *im yesh bahen achrayut nechasim*,
if there are liens, לא יחזיר *lo yachzir*, don't give it back
to ראובן *Reuven* who's the מלווה malve *malveh* because then he'll come
to take not just the property from שמעון *Shimon* but he'll come
to take it from people שמעון *Shimon* has sold his property to
שבית דין נפרעין מהם *shebeit din nifra'in mehem* because בית דין *beit
din* would then extract that property. אין בהן אחריות נכסים Ein bahen
achrayut nechasim, *ein bahen achrayut nechasim*, if there are no liens, יחזיר
*yachzir*, then you can return it to ראובן *Reuven* שאין בית דין
נפרעין מהם *she'ein beit din nifra'in mehem* because בית דין *beit din*
will not collect, דברי רבי מאיר divrei Rabbi Meir. *divrei Rabi Meir*,
that's Rabi Meir's view, which is of course very bizarre because it's
all very nice that the people שמעון *Shimon* sold the property to
are not going to have their property seized, but what is שמעון
*Shimon* saying in all of this? Why is שמעון *Shimon* going to
be allowed to be having this document given back to ראובן *Reuven*?
וחכמים אומרים V'Chachamim omrim, *vachachamim omrim*, and the חכמים Chachamim *chachamim* say,
בין כך ובין כך לא יחזיר *bein kach uvein kach lo yachzir*,
whether there are liens or not liens, don't give it to ראובן
*Reuven* מפני שבית דין נפרעין מהם *mipnei shebeit din nifra'in mehem* because
either way בית דין *beit din* will use it to collect. Okay,
so very interesting why the liens should matter and what about poor
שמעון *Shimon* who presumably is saying that he no longer owes the
money, it's a forgery or he paid it up or whatever. So
we are going to see the basic question that's going to dominate
the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*, no not the basic question that's going to
dominate the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is what is שמעון *Shimon* saying? Maybe
the case is talking that שמעון *Shimon* even admits he owes the
money. So let's take a look.
במאי עסקינן *bemai askinan*, what are we talking about? אילימא כשחייב מודה
*eilima kshechayav
modeh*, if it's that שמעון *Shimon* admits that he owes the money,
כי יש בהן אחריות achrayus, נכסים אמאי לא יחזיר amai lo yachzir,
*ki yesh bahen achrayut nechasim amai lo yachzir*, why not give it
back to ראובן *Reuven*? המודה הוא *hamodeh hu*, he admits. ואי כשאין
חייב מודה *ve'i kshe'ein chayav modeh*, and if שמעון *Shimon* is not
admitting he owes the money, כי אין בהן אחריות achrayus
נכסים אמאי amai, יחזיר *ki ein bahen achrayut nechasim amai yachzir*?
Even if there are no liens, why give it back? נהי דלא
גבי ממשעבדי *nehi dela gabi mimeshuabadei*, even if ראובן *Reuven* cannot collect
from the encumbered property, מבני חרי מיהא גבי *mibnei charei miha gabi*,
he'll collect from the unencumbered property, he'll collect from the chattel, okay
that's still under שמעון *Shimon*'s control. Okay, so okay maybe it does
belong to ראובן *Reuven*, but maybe it doesn't. Why have we just
decided it's okay to give it to ראובן *Reuven* if there are
no liens? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לעולם כשחייב מודה *le'olam
kshechayav modeh*, so the first round of interpretations of this משנה Mishna.
*Mishnah* is going to be that שמעון *Shimon* admits he owes the
money. והכא היינו טעמא *vehacha hainu ta'ama*, here's the reason why even
if שמעון *Shimon* admits he owes the money we're going to hesitate
to give it back to ראובן *Reuven*. והכא היינו טעמא דחיישינן שמא
כתב ללוות בניסן ולא לוה loveh עד תשרי Tishrei *vehacha hainu ta'ama
dechashinan shema katav lilvot beNisan velo lava ad Tishrei*. Even if he
admits he owes the money, so as soon as you say we're
talking about that he admits he owes the money then the whole
issue in the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* therefore is going to be a
concern for the לקוחות lakochot *lakochot*, a concern for the people who
bought property from שמעון *Shimon*. Now that's probably the easy way to
read the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah*. Since the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* only seems
to be concerned about the issue of liens, presumably we're not concerned
for שמעון *Shimon*. Why are we not concerned for שמעון *Shimon*? Presumably
because he admits he owes the money. If you admit you owe
the money, גזונטהייט *gesundheit*, we're not concerned about you, you're admitting, why
should we be concerned? But is it fair that your admission might
potentially hurt the people that bought the property from you, and maybe
the loan really doesn't exist? Now why should we assume that, why
what should we assume the problem would be, why would you say
the loan did exist if it didn't, why should we be concerned
about them? So here's scenario number one, scenario number one is: yes
the loan exists, yes you're telling the truth, but maybe the liens
really are later than they say they are. The document says you
borrowed a thousand dollars in ניסן Nisan *Nisan* and you really didn't
borrow it, because the documents start being dated from ניסן Nissan, *Nisan*,
that's the new year for documents, and you really didn't borrow it
till תשרי Tishrei. *Tishrei*. So therefore the documents are really giving six
months of liens that are not deserved and that's why we don't
want to return it to ראובן *Reuven*. Yes you owe the money,
or you admit you owe the money, no problem, but nevertheless we're
afraid about those poor לקוחות lakochot *lakochot* because maybe the document is
not properly dated.
So if you're admitting it's the same amount of money and the
same you know it's the same parties to the transaction, why would
you think that really you know it didn't really happen until later?
Well right that's the question why of all documents should we concern
that this one doesn't have the right date? So that's what we're
going to ask. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. והכא
היינו טעמא דחיישינן שמא כתב ללוות בניסן ולא לוה loveh עד תשרי
Tishrei, *vehacha hainu ta'ama dechashinan shema katav lilvot beNisan velo lava ad
Tishrei*. ואתו וטרפו לקוחות lakuchos, שלא כדין *ve'atu vatarfu lakochot shelo kedin*,
right, which is the best read of the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah*, the
משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* seems primarily to really only be concerned about. about
the purchasers of שמעון'ס property, and so therefore he's admitting it's not
a problem about שמעון, but it's about the problem but it's about
the lien and it's about the people that purchased. What is the
concern for them? The concern is that the document, the liens of
the document didn't start till six months after they were written, and
therefore those לקוחות lakochos, will be unjustly out of their property. So
אי הכי ihachi says גמרא, Gemara okay, that's all very nice, but
כל שטרא דאתו לקמן, kol shtra de-asu lekaman, why all of a
sudden are we concerned with this document? Any document of a loan,
ניחוש להו, neichosh lehu, let's be concerned that it was written in
ניסן Nissan but it wasn't used until תשרי Tishrei. and that the
date in it gives the person liens that he's not entitled to.
ניחוש הכי, neichosh hachi, let's have a similar concern. It says no,
כל שטרי לא רעי הני רעי, kol shtarei lo rai hanei rai,
all other documents have not been challenged but thrown
under suspicion. This one has become suspect. Now the question is what
is the logic behind that? רש"י Rashi sort of says that the
logic is well if this were a completely up and up legitimate
document you would have been more careful with it. The fact that
you lost it shows that there was something a little fishy about
the document and maybe that's why you weren't so careful. Okay now
that seems a little far-fetched. I mean if I'm going to go
ahead and I have a document that you owe me $10,000 and
it gives me I don't know three months liens earlier than I'm
deserved than I'm entitled to I'm going to be sloppy with it
because it gives me a few extra months of liens? I mean
it's $10,000 that's tied up in this document. So the sort of
the real rational logic that because we found it it proves that
somehow there's something suspicious seems a little yeah that seems a little
strange. Okay so therefore this led as I said I think I
said a few days ago there's a more sort of למדות lamdus
approach to this is the idea that as soon as the document
is not being held by the person who it's testifying on their
behalf, it's not being held by the מלוה, malveh, it starts it
stops being seen as testimony. The whole idea is that a written
document is כמי שנחקרה עדותן בבית דין. ke-mi she-nechakrei eidutun be-veit din.
It's like I have testimony in court. The question is what's the
story about a document on the street? Since already there's a question
who dropped it, what's its story, was it ever used? So even
if afterwards the לוה loveh said yes I did draw it up,
yes the מלוה malveh does have it, yes it is legitimate, by
giving it to the מלוה malveh we're taking a document that at
this stage is a piece of paper with words on it and
we're turning it into עדות eidus by giving it to the מלוה
malveh and now empowering him to use it and to use it
to testify in his behalf. So to do that, to turn it
into עדות, eidus, any like slight question should make us pause and
hesitate before we effectively transform this from a piece of paper into
עדות eidus by giving it over to the מלוה. malveh. So that's
the sort of other way to read it. It's not like there's
a logical connection. Oh since we found it must be it's not
a 100% of a legitimate document otherwise you wouldn't have been sloppy.
Excuse me document that says somebody owes me a million dollars worth
I'm not going to be sloppy with just because it was written
a month before it was able to be used. Okay so it's
more of a point that no no by handing it over we're
changing its whole identity and its nature and for that we want
to be really certain. So that's like the more למדות lamdus explanation
behind this. Okay but either way here's the point. You've got this
document and therefore if there are liens and the לקוחות lokuchos, could
be hurt by it and there's the possibility that somehow it's not
the liens are not 100% written properly in the document maybe they
were written before the money was borrowed and therefore the liens started
too early. If there's even that slight possibility which always exists by
any document but because it exists we're not going to return the
document.
Yes even if both again even if both parties really did happen
that day? Correct. And עדים edim were there? They saw it happen?
That's correct. So
we will not return it. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Will the עדים edim be able to force
if they have עדים edim who actually say it and the עדים
edim can go ahead and write another document? Yeah. Okay so now
the גמרא Gemara says I don't know if the עדים edim themselves
say it maybe we would return it. Okay so the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
הני רעי. hanei rai. So this one
has had suspicions cast aspersions cast upon it. והדתניא ve-ha de-tanyia that's
what we taught in the משנה Mishnah, כותבין שטר ללוה אף על
פי שאין מלוה עמו. kotvin shtar le-loveh af al pi she-ein malveh
imo. לכתחילה היכי כתבינן הו. le-chatchilah heichi katvinan hu. One minute says
the גמרא Gemara now he raises an important question because we've taught
and we taught this the other day that if I want to
borrow $10,000 there from Michael I go to my two pals David
and Charlie and I say David write a document that I borrowed
$10,000 from Michael and you know you can write it for me
because it's only going to hurt me and you can sign it
and I'm going to go to Michael and I'm going to get
him to lend me the money and then I'll give him the
document and this way I'll have the document all ready to do
it so maybe it'll encourage him to give me the money. So
you're allowed to do that because I'm only hurting myself. Okay the
problem is if I don't get a hold of Michael or I
don't convince him for three months from now and he actually does
lend me the money and I give him the document that's dated
today, he's going to have liens three months before the loan. So
we've... Now raise an important question, right? You raised the important question
about a document that was written before the money was borrowed, and
you're right. It's not fair. It gives him liens too soon. But
then how do we ever allow the document to be written for
the לווה love then? Maybe it'll take time until he gets the
מלווה malve to lend him the money. Okay. הלא הדתנן כותבין שטר
ללווה אף על פי שאין מלווה עמו. hala hadatnan kotvin shtar lilove
af pi she'ein malve imo. You can write a שטר shtar. for
the לווה love even if the מלווה malve isn't there because it's
only hurting the לווה, love, but how do you do that? לכתחילה
הכי כתבינן? lechatchila hachi katvinan? How do we allow that to happen?
ניחוש שמא כתב ללוות בניסן ולווה בתשרי. neichosh shema katav lilovos beNissan
velavah beTishrei. You're writing it for the לווה, love, it's now in
ניסן, Nissan but he doesn't get the guy to lend him the
money until
תשרי. ואתי למטרף לקוחות שלא כדין. ve'asi lemitraf lakuchos shelo kedin. And
it's going to give the מלווה malve the right to collect property
improperly, you know, property not legally or not properly because he doesn't
really get those liens until the money is lent, but the liens
are written as of the day of the writing. So אמר רב
אסי, amar Rav Assi, that's a good general question which you could
have asked at any time during the year, okay, but we happen
to be asking it right now. Thank you, Jonah. Okay, so well
there you go. Good point. So אמר רב אסי בשטר
הקנאה הוא. amar Rav Assi beshtar hakna'ah hu.
דשעביד נפשיה. dashiv beneifshei. Jonah, I believe you actually asked this question
when we saw this teaching about a week ago, right, which is
how do you write a document early? How do you write a
document before borrowing the money if the money is borrowed later, it's
giving you liens of too early of a date. So it says,
you know what, you're right. You're right. The only time you would
write a document for the לווה love without the מלווה malve there
would be a שטר הקנאה. shtar hakna'ah. A שטר הקנאה shtar hakna'ah
means to, you know,
to transfer, well not exactly, like to transfer ownership. And what it
means is that a שטר הקנאה shtar hakna'ah is you guys, I
go to my friends Charlie and David and I say Charlie, write
I
borrowed ten thousand dollars from Michael and we're going to write a
certain נוסח nusach in the שטר. shtar, Okay, exactly what that נוסח
nusach is not clear, I mean I'm sure it is clear but
I don't know it anyway right now, but anyway that נוסח nusach
is basically saying that I am doing a קניין kinyan to give
Michael the liens on my property as of today. Even though I
might not wind up borrowing that money for like six months, he
gets those liens as of today. And we might find out later
not only does he have those liens of today, maybe even
if I never get him to lend me the money, you know
maybe he can also collect. I mean there's two questions: when do
the liens start and is it dependent on him eventually lending me
the money? Right, to understand it would make sense to say well
okay fine he has the liens as of today assuming eventually he
lends me the money. Let's say he never lends me the money,
am I just giving him those liens straight out? Okay. But that's
what a שטר הקנאה... shtar hakna'ah...
does it mean I can get ten thousand dollars that I never
lent you back? Yep.
I mean I can obligate myself to you money that I never
borrowed from you so I can give you liens of money I
never borrowed. Now I'm hoping you'll lend me the money, but maybe
even if you don't. Okay, so that's a separate question. Does he
eventually have to lend me the money? But whether eventually he does
or not, by doing the special קניין kinyan with the עדים, eidim,
you know I'll take a handkerchief, I do a קניין kinyan and
we write in the שטר, shtar I have given Michael those liens
as of today. So therefore and presumably there's enough of a record
of that or a report of that or people find out about
it so the לקוחות, lukuachas. people who would buy my property are
considered to be protected because I did this קניין kinyan and we
wrote the document even though I haven't borrowed the money yet. Okay.
So that when are you guys allowed to write a document for
me before Michael lends me the money? Only when I do this
קניין kinyan and I grant Michael the liens as of today. And
then when eventually he borrows the money, he will be genuinely entitled
to the liens from the day of the writing. But if I
don't do that then you shouldn't agree to write the שטר shtar
for me because then I'll borrow the money six months from now,
he'll only have the liens six months from now, but the document
will say he has the liens as of today and that's not
fair to people who might potentially purchase my property.
Okay. So שטר שבו אחריות, shtar shebo achrayus, that wouldn't be a
problem either?
Right, if it's שטר שבו אחריות shtar shebo achrayus what else is
fine, correct.
And
I would do that as the debtor because I really need the
money and these are the only terms under which the creditor, he
wants those liens accessible now.
Yeah, or because I also
know that... right, or yes, and or because I know that the
only way I'll get him to lend me the money is if
I come with the document already written, and the only way I'm
going to be able to come with the document already written is
if I give him the liens as of now because otherwise it
would be it would not be legal to write a document like
that which would predate the loan. The only way you can write
a document that would predate the loan, like the classic שטר shtar
חוב that's invalid is שטר חוב מוקדמים shtar chov mukdamim that they
predate. So by the way so that would mean so because then
it gives liens that I'm not entitled to. So the only way
I'm entitled to do this, it's not predating today's date, but it
might predate the loan because who knows when he's going to lend
me the money, is by granting him the lien as of today.
Okay. So yes. So בשטר הקנאה, beshtar hakna, that's the only time
they can write the document not in the מלווה's malveh, presence. דשעביד
נפשיה, dashiv beneifshei, because you are encumbering yourself legitimately as of today.
even before the money is lent. אי הכי, ei hachi, okay, so
now we've said that the only way in which it'll be written
before the loan is in this special case. So now we're going
to come back to our משנה. Mishnah. אי הכי, ei hachi, מתניתין
דקתני אם יש בה אחריות נכסים לא יחזיר, masnisin de-katani im yesh
bah achrayus nechasim lo yachzir,
the משנה Mishnah, that says that if there is liens in the
document, don't give it back to the מלווה, malveh ואוקימנא כשחייב מודה,
v'ukimna k'she-chayav modeh, and we said that's even if the לווה loveh
agrees, don't give it back to the מלווה malveh? because maybe the
liens will be prior to the loan and that won't be fair
to the poor לקוחות, lukuachas. ומשום שמא כתב ללוות בניסן ולא לוה
עד תשרי, u-mishum shema kasav lilvos be-Nissan ve-lo lovah ad Tishrei, exactly
that, because it was written on ניסן but the money wasn't borrowed
until תשרי, ואתי למיטרף לקוחות שלא כדין, v'asi l'mitraf lakochos she-lo kedin,
and the purchasers, he'll seize property from the purchasers unjustly. אמאי, so
why still, why still can we not return the document to the
מלווה? malveh. אמאי לא יחזיר, נחזי, nechezi, let's see what type of
document we're talking about. אי בשטרי הקנאה, ei be-shtarei hakna'ah, if it's
a loan document that has this קנין kinyan that the liens were
effective as of the date it was written, so if that's true,
הדרי ליה לנפשיה, hadrei lei l'nafsheih, so give it back to the
מלווה. malveh Those liens legitimately exist from the date it was written
regardless of when the money was borrowed. אי בשטר דלאו הקנאה, ei
be-shtar de-lav hakna'ah, if it doesn't have this קנין kinyan and it
does not have this special act of encumbering yourself from the date
it was written, so what are we concerned about? That it was
written before the money was borrowed? But one minute, ליכא למיחש, leika
lemichash,
there's nothing to worry about. דאמרת, de-amart, you just got through saying,
כי ליכא מלווה בהדיה לא כתבינן, ki leika malveh bahadeih lo kasvinan,
if the מלווה malveh isn't there and they're not actually in the
process of borrowing the money and lending the money,
the עדים edim shouldn't agree to write it, right? So we've just
said, you just said there's a problem it might be written before
the money is borrowed. So we've pointed out, okay, then that's always
a problem, how do עדים edim ever sign a document? And you've
basically said you're right, עדים edim should never sign a document except
in one of two cases. A, the money is actually being lent
right now, or B, it's a שטר הקנאה shtar hakna'ah and the
liens are being created right now. So if that's true, there'll never
be a document that'll be a problem, so we should always agree
to return a שטר shtar if the לווה loveh agrees. There's never
a scenario where it'll be dated prior to the money actually being
borrowed. Now of course it could be that I hired some unsavory
witnesses and told them to pre-date it, and maybe the whole שטר
shtar is מזויף mezuyaf too, but we're at this stage we're not
concerned that somebody is going to actually be doing an act of
like real deception and רשעות. rishus. Okay, if that's true let's be
concerned that the שטר shtar is a forgery. That level of concern
we're not up to, we're up to concerns about normal types of
scenarios that might happen. So the גמרא's Gemara saying there's no normal
scenario that this will happen. I'll take your questions let's first see
the גמרא's Gemara answer. So the גמרא Gemara, answers it, אמר ליה
רב אסי, amar lei Rav Assi,
Rav Assi said back, אף על גב דשטר דלאו הקנאה כי ליכא
מלווה בהדיה לא כתבינן, af al gav de-shtar de-lav hakna'ah ki leika
malveh bahadeih lo kasvinan, even though when it's not a שטר הקנאה
shtar hakna'ah we would not write it if the מלווה malveh isn't
there and the money isn't being lent right there then and there,
so there should be no legitimate scenario of it pre-dating, מתניתין כיון
דנפל, masnisin keivan de-nafal, in our
משנה, Mishnah? once the שטר shtar has fallen and it's on the
ground, איתרע ליה, isra lei, it has been, it has been like
suspicion has been laid, it's been impugned. Thank you, that's a good
word. Did you use the word impugned? Thank you, good word. It's
been impugned וחיישינן דילמא איקרי וכתב ve-chaishinan dilma ikrei ve-kasav
and maybe this was a שטר shtar that the עדים edim were
not paying attention to protocol. I went to the עדים, edim, I
went to my friends Charlie and David, I said, Charlie, David, I
know, I know you're not supposed to write it unless Michael is
here, but you know what, he promised me he's going to lend
the money, I'm running away, I'm going to go catch him at
the train station, please, please do me a favor, just write it
now, don't do שטר הקנאה shtar hakna'ah whatever I don't have the
time, just let's do it. Okay, and you guys, you know, you
were so sensitive and you I was able to persuade you, you
did it. So you might there might be a case where they
broke protocol and they did and they did it. And that's what
we're concerned about. Of course to be say that all these cases
the מלווה malveh agrees, the לווה loveh agrees, under any
under all normal circumstances no type of problematic שטר shtar? should ever
exist, but we're going to be concerned that this happened over in
a שטר shtar where the עדים edim broke protocol and signed it
without the מלווה malveh being there and we're not going to return
it seems quite far-fetched. And this is why as I said, you
know, this explanation develops in the more contemporary אחרונים achronim to not
say that there's really like a logic, oh, well, most likely there
is a problem or else I wouldn't have dropped it, like give
me a break, what's the chances it really is a problematic שטר?
shtar But it's more because by giving it back to the מלווה
malveh we're re-establishing it as a שטר shtar. and as עדות eidus
and therefore, you know, the fact that now when it says איתרע
ליה isra lei it means a שטר shtar on the ground is
not a שטר. shtar And we're going to transform it into a
שטר shtar, by handing it back, so any possible concern is going
to make us hesitate. Yes, Charlie.
So on a typical שומר שבת shomer Shabbos from birth,
and I understand שבת Shabbos law, but I don't understand all these
details of what kind of שטר shtar I can sign at what
time that I can't.
Well, that's a way of explaining why the case of it that
it's happened that you that you violated protocol. Like you, you know,
I can just חאפ chap two people and say sign the שטר,
shtar right? And it is true that if
you were Maybe it's not so crazy, right? The scenario I gave
was you knew the rule but I persuaded you to break it.
But you're right, there may be a lot of scenarios that they
don't even know the rule. So that's a very good point. Yes.
Another question was, does it also make a difference where you found
it? Because you said it's really unusual to find it like in
a garbage dump or something. So obviously he found it. But if
you find it like on the street, you know, and then there's
more of a chance that he dropped it.
Yeah, so there's
being discarded because it's trashy.
I understand. There's a little bit of that coming up, but the
Sages are certainly not distinguishing those cases. But there's a little of
that coming up. Any other points? Okay, so let's—so that's answer number
one. Answer number one is, which works because the whole משנה Mishnah.
emphasizes the idea that there's אחריות, achrayus that the concern is about
the לקוחות, lukuachas, about the people that might have bought my property.
And the possible concern is that it was written before the money
was borrowed, even though that never should have happened. Okay, now we're
going to have a variation of that. אביי אמר, Abaye amar,
now אביי, Abaye, אביי's Abaye answer here is not yet to explain
the משנה, Mishnah אביי's Abaye answer here is to explain the rule
that I can get witnesses to sign a שטר shtar even without
borrowing the money yet. And our question was, one minute, won't that
lead to predated
liens? Okay, remember that was our question. So answer number one was
the only time עדים eidim are supposed to do that is in
a special scenario of a שטר הקנאה, shtar hakna'ah, where I do
a קנין kinyan to create the liens today regardless. אביי Abaye is
going to say you don't need a special scenario. Anytime witnesses sign
a שטר shtar, that I borrowed money today from Michael, even though
I haven't, okay, the act of signing that שטר shtar creates the
liens as of today, even if I don't borrow the money until
six months from now. The liens are created as of today. That's
אביי's Abaye concept, that a שטר, shtar every שטר shtar is effectively
a שטר הקנאה. shtar hakna'ah. אביי אמר עדי החתומה זכין לו. Abaye
amar edei hachasumah zachin lo. The witnesses with their signatures are, you
know, award me—not me—award Michael the lien. The act of signing the
שטר shtar gives him the liens even before the money is borrowed.
Every שטר shtar is effectively a שטר הקנאה. shtar hakna'ah. Now here's
the difference, though. The difference is that a שטר הקנאה shtar hakna'ah
might mean even if I never borrow the money from Michael, maybe
I've just given him the lien straight out, and he's got that
right to seize my property even without the money ever having been
borrowed. A שטר shtar that's not הקנאה, hakna'ah, that's an important difference
even with אביי, Abaye, okay, awards him the liens, assuming that the
money eventually will be borrowed. All right, so that's still the difference,
there is still a reality of שטר הקנאה shtar hakna'ah for אביי,
Abaye, but nevertheless, אביי Abaye says the act of signing the שטר
shtar creates the liens as of that date, even if the money
isn't borrowed until later. So for אביי, Abaye, there's never a problem
for witnesses to sign a שטר shtar without the לווה loveh being
there, because the liens are created as of today. This still doesn't
explain why we can't return the שטר shtar. in the משנה. mishna
We gotta go back, we're going to go back in a little
bit to say, so why can't you return the שטר shtar in
the משנה, mishna. because the liens are always legitimate in any type
of a שטר. shtar Yes?
Would this hold up in court if somebody gave this and they
never received any money?
If it was a שטר הקנאה, shtar hakna'ah, yes. Yeah. A שטר
הקנאה shtar hakna'ah basically is just out and out awarding those that—that
to the other person. Okay, now if the other person lends me
money, it's awarding it in the—it's not like I awarded it to
him and if he lends me money I also owe him another
amount of money on top of it. It's awarding to him in
this fiction that he has lent me money. But whether in the
end he has or he hasn't, right, a שטר הקנאה shtar hakna'ah
just straight out gives him that—those rights. Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Okay. So, ואפילו שטרי דלאו הקנאה, ve-afilu shtarei
de-lav hakna'ah, and even a שטר shtar that's not הקנאה. hakna'ah. משום
דקשיא ליה, mishum de-kashya leh, because it was—he was bothered. כיון דאמרת
בשטרי דלאו הקנאה כי ליתא למלוה בהדיה לא כתבינן, keivan de-amret beshtarei
de-lav hakna'ah ki leisa le-malveh behadeh lo katvinan, now we've got a
problem, right? If you say with a שטר shtar that's not הקנאה,
hakna'ah, if the מלווה malveh isn't there when—we shouldn't be writing it—that
was what we were saying before. So ליכא למיחש דאקרי וכתב, leika
le-michash de-ikri ve-katav, he doesn't buy that—oh, like his—this read of the
משנה. mishna? If you're never supposed to do it, then we're not
going to be concerned that it's going to happen. So that can't
be what's going on in the משנה, mishna that oh, you weren't
supposed to sign it but maybe you did. So what is going
on in the משנה? mishna We don't know yet. But the first
point is you do not have to make a special case of
שטר הקנאה. shtar hakna'ah. The idea that you can write it without
the מלווה malveh is every case, because the fact of signing creates
the liens as of today. Okay, so what that—so now we're going
to challenge that and then we're going to go back and explain
the משנה. mishna So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אלא הא
דתנן... elah had-tenan...
what was ליכא למיחש דאקרי וכתב? leika le-michash de-ikri ve-katav?
If you're not supposed to sign without the מלווה malveh there, then
there would—you—it's never legitimate to say maybe it happened. There's no reason
to... It happened... to say it happened, right, exactly. Okay. אלא הא
דתנן, elah had-tenan, so fine, let's work with אביי, Abaye, that the
signature creates the reality. אלא הא דתנן, elah had-tenan, that which we
taught in the משנה mishna coming up. מצא גיטי נשים, matza gitei
nashim, if you find a bill of divorce, ושחרורי עבדים veshichrurei avadim
or a writ of manumission, a freeing of a slave. דיאטיקי, dyatiki,
which is a שטר shtar that testifies to a deathbed request, bequest,
excuse me. דיאטיקי, dyatiki, מתנה matanah or a—just a simple gift document.
ושוברים, ve-shovrim, or a receipt... Do not return it to the person
who is the intended recipient of that, the woman, the slave, all
the people, the receiver of the gift, etc. Why? שכתובים היו ונמלך
עליהם שלא ליתנם. she-ktuvim hayu v'nimlach aleihem she-lo litnam.
Maybe they were written with the intent of freeing the slave, divorcing
the wife, giving the gift, but then the guy changed his mind.
Okay, so obviously that would be a case of אין חייב מודה.
ein chayav modeh. The guy isn't admitting or maybe the guy isn't
around. So don't just give those and you don't know that they've
ever actually been given or not. Okay. And by the way that's
very different than a loan document. A loan document you assume is
never going to be written until the money has changed hands, right?
Whereas a גט get could be written while I'm still debating whether
or not to divorce my wife. I've got a גט get but
whether I'm debating whether or not to free my slave, I've got
this stuff maybe it doesn't happen immediately after the event of the
writing. Okay. שטר הקנאה. shtar hakna'ah. Well, right. So that's going to
be the question. But for אביי, Abaye, every document is effective as
of the date it's signed. So the גמרא Gemara says וכי נמלך
עליהם מאי הוי v'chi nimlach aleihem mai havay says גמרא, Gemara but
who cares if you haven't if you've changed your mind? והאמרת, ve-ha-amarta,
you've said אביי, Abaye, עדים בחתימתן זכין לו. eidim be-chasiman zachin lo.
The signatures cause it to be effective. Now the question is
how far did the גמרא Gemara think that he said it by
loans. Did he think a גט get takes effect the moment it's
signed? Like clearly, now it's important to distinguish between two types of
שטרות, shtaros, right? There's a שטר shtar. that is basically about testifying
to the reality of something, and that's just called a שטר ראיה,
shtar ra'aya, like it's signed testimony. And there's a שטר shtar that's
an instrument, right, which is called in halachic language a שטר קנין.
shtar kinyan. Like a גט get is fundamentally an instrument of divorce,
right? A שטר שחרור shtar shichrur is an instrument of freeing the
slave. A שטר מתנה shtar matana is an instrument of transferring the
land. But here's the thing, since אביי Abaye says the signature creates
the liens, so it's not the loan that's creating the liens, it's
the signature. So he's basically saying the signature works as a type
of an instrument of effecting a halachic change, right? The signing itself
created those liens. So it sounds like the גמרא gemara is thinking
maybe it works even to avoid the need of having to hand
over the שטר. shtar The signature is the instrument. But it's again
it's hard to think the גמרא Gemara thinks it by something like
a גט. get. But maybe the גמרא Gemara is at least asking
by the case of like the gift. Like the שטר מתנה, shtar
matana, right? If it works by ממונות mamonus ideas and can it
give you liens on my property by the fact they signed it,
then maybe the fact they signed it should give you ownership of
my property. Maybe you shouldn't need it to be handed over. Okay
so at least by some of these shouldn't אביי's Abaye principle of
עדים בחתימתן זכין לו eidim be-chasiman zachin lo effect the change without
it actually being handed over? וכי נמלך עליהם מאי הוי והאמרת עדים
בחתימתן זכין לו. v'chi nimlach aleihem mai havay ve-ha-amarta eidim be-chasiman zachin
lo. The עדים eidim with their signature award the property. So the
גמרא Gemara, says no הני מילי היכא דמטו לידיה. hani mili heicha
de-matu l'yadei. That's only once the שטר shtar, is eventually given over,
it takes effect retroactively from the date that it was signed. Okay.
But one minute היכא דמטו לידיה אבל היכא דלא מטו לידיה לא
אמרינן. heicha de-matu l'yadei aval heicha de-la matu l'yadei lo amrinan. But
if you never give it over, no, it's not the signature by
itself. And again that's the difference between this and a שטר הקנאה.
shtar hakna'ah. A שטר הקנאה shtar hakna'ah I don't have to give
the שטר shtar, over, I don't have to or maybe I have
to give the שטר, shtar I don't have to borrow the money
or something. Okay but this שטר, shtar it's not saying I am
giving it to you as of today. The שטר shtar is just
a normal שטר shtar with signatures. But what אביי Abaye is saying
is is that when the שטר shtar is given over, the signatures
give you the rights as of the day it was written. Now
does he really mean this by גט? get? I write a גט
get to divorce my wife today, I get the witnesses to sign,
I don't give it to her for three years from now. When
I give it to her three years from now she's retroactively divorced
as of today? It would seem that there's a big difference between
personal status issues and money issues. But maybe he does mean it
by a מתנה. matana. I gift my piece of land there to
Jenna and I get the witnesses to sign it and I don't
give it to her for a year from now. Maybe when I
do give it to her retroactively she owns it as of today?
Okay, because maybe a מתנה, matana, the idea of זכין לו zachin
lo like a זכות, zechus, right, the same way I could have
given it to we could have done a little קנין סודר kinyan
sudar and I could have given it to her today. So if
I get them to sign a שטר shtar, and I give her
the שטר shtar three years from now then maybe she does own
it retroactively as of today.
So then if you owned it what maybe she'd pay
rent for the last maybe you would if you were smart you
would do that
assuming you were still only a year later she has to
pay back there you go. Okay, so this is a really fascinating
idea of אביי Abaye of עדים בחתימתן זכין לו. eidim be-chasiman zachin
lo. Although we're dealing with a משנה mishna? that throws in גט
get and שטר שחרור, shtar shichrur, we're going to assume that those
are clearly different cases. But at least in ממונות mamonus cases which
א' aleph it's ממונות mamonus and ב' beis it's a זכות, zechus,
okay, those at least we אביי Abaye is saying that when you
since presumably you could do it as of now through any other
קנין, kinyan, through a סודר sudar or something like that, the act
of having them sign it makes it take effect as of now,
but since they're doing it in the context of a שטר, shtar,
on the condition that the שטר shtar is eventually given over. given,
it takes effect as of now. So when I have עדים eidim
write sign a loan document, the liens don't exist now, they'll exist
retroactively now when I eventually borrow the money and when I eventually
hand over the שטר, shtar okay? So that's a very important principle
of אביי. Abaye. עדים בחותמיהן זכין לו. eidim bichatuman zachun lo. You
have to eventually give it over, but if you eventually give it
over, it exists as of now. A שטר קנייה shtar knaya might
be different, might be you don't even have to give it over,
maybe you don't even have to borrow the money, but a normal
שטר shtar with עדות edus that's ממונות, momunus, retroactively takes effect as
of the date that it was signed assuming that eventually it was
given over. All right? So that's now just clarifying אביי's Abaye position.
So back to where we were. אביי Abaye says you can always
sign a loan document if the מלווה malveh isn't there because retroactively
the מלווה malveh. will legitimately have liens from the date it was
signed. So back to our משנה. mishna Why not return the שטר
shtar in our משנה? Mishnah So now let's take a look. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: אלא מתניתין דקתני מצא שטר
חוב, ella matnisin d'katanei matza shtar chov, our משנה Mishnah, says when
you find these debt documents, אם יש בהן אחריות נכסים לא יחזיר,
im yesh bahen achrayus nechasim lo yachzir, if there are אחריות achrayus
don't give it back. וקים לן כשחייב מודה, vekim lan keshechayev modeh,
and we said until now we're talking about the guy admitted that
he borrowed the money, the לווה loveh admitted, but we're concerned to
protect the לקוחות. lukuachas. ומשום שמא כתב ללוות בניסן ולא לווה עד
תשרי. umishum shema kasav lilvos b'nisan velo lova ad tishrei.
We don't want to give him back because maybe it was dated
before the money was borrowed. בשלמא לרב אסי דאמר בשטרי אקנייתא. bishlama
l'Rav Assi d'amar b'shtarei aknayasa.
So we're a little repeating ourselves. That works for רב אסי Rav
Assi that says that it's only by a שטר קניין shtar kinyan
that the liens are from the date it was signed. That's and
that's when the עדים eidim can sign it without the money being
borrowed. מוקי לה בשטרי דלא אקנייתא. mokilei b'shtarei d'la aknayasa. This is
a שטר shtar that's not a שטר קניין, shtar kinyan, and even
though you're normally not supposed to have signed it וכדאמרן u'cheda'amen and
we explained we're concerned that maybe the עדים eidim violated protocol and
they did sign it and they are they do give him illegitimate
liens. So that's the
problem. אלא אביי דאמר עדים בחותמיהן זכין לו, ella Abaye d'amar eidim
bichatuman zachun lo, but אביי Abaye says that any signature retroactively gives
the guy liens from the time that it was signed. מאי איכא
למימר? maika lemeimar? Why what can you say? There's no good reason
not to give it back to the מלווה. malveh? Everybody agrees the
money was borrowed, and therefore he's entitled to the liens from the
date in the document. אמר לך אביי מתניתין היינו טעמא דחייא של
פירעון וקנוניא. amar lach Abaye matnisin hainu ta'ama dechaya shel piron u'knunya.
So this is another explanation, not that there was somehow a problem
in the document, but that there is a scheme that is going
on. פירעון piron means that it's been paid up and there's a
קנוניא. knunya. So basically here's what happened. I paid up my thousand
dollars to Michael. He gave me the שטר shtar. back. And then
I said, you know what, Michael, I got a great idea. I
sold some property there to Charlie, okay? And Charlie was stupid enough,
sorry Charlie, to buy that property without getting insurance from me. Okay,
the insurance I would normally give him is that if any creditor
came and took the property I would reimburse him. But he didn't
take that insurance out from me. So here's what we're going to
do. We're going to say I didn't pay the debt. You're I'm
going to give you back the document. You're going to go and
ask me for the money. I'm going to say I don't have
it, because now I don't have any money left. You're going to
go and seize the property from Charlie, okay? He can't come back
to me because I didn't give him insurance, and we'll split the
property you get from Charlie, okay?
So that's 75 percent.
What? I'm 75 percent? 75? All right, I'm holding out for 50
percent. So that's פירעון piron is I paid it up, and קנוניא
knunya is the scheme that we've got going on to basically cheat
the לקוחות. lukuachas. Now of course that could happen any single time.
Anybody comes to collect property and I say I'm out, go get
it from the לקוחות, lakuchos we could say oh well maybe you
actually did pay and there's a scheme going on. But we're back
to the point. Under normal circumstances we don't suspect those things. But
the שטר shtar now has fallen. It stops being an effective שטר.
shtar I'm going to go with that explanation because I like it
so much. To turn this into testimony that can now be used
against Charlie and to take property away from Charlie, okay, just because
I'm saying it, that's it's going to hurt not hurt me, it's
going to hurt Charlie, we're not going to turn it into that
testimony as long as there's some possibility that there's something fishy going
on here.
This document was supposed to be
in the hands of the עדים? eidim? Yes, well I'm not sure
that, but yeah, good, what's the question?
We all we all worry about אחריות טעות סופר, achrayus ta'us sofer,
right?
Which is why which is why the משנה Mishnah.
is that if it's
got אחריות achrayus you don't return. Exactly, which is why the משנה
Mishnah? says if it's got אחריות achrayus you don't return it. And
the other opinion in the משנה Mishnah that says even if it
doesn't have אחריות achrayus we're going to see in a few minutes
basically says that even if אחריות achrayus is not written explicitly in
the document it's always assumed to be there. So the basic way
according to this, which we should have said before also, because any
explanation we've given now is only to protect the לקוחות. lakuchos So
what's the debate in the משנה? Mishnah According to this, as we'll
say in a few minutes, the only debate in the משנה Mishnah
is, or we'll say tomorrow, is whether a document without the אחריות
achrayus written explicitly is presumed to have the אחריות achrayus? anyway. That's
the question of אחריות טעות סופר. achrayus ta'us sofer. Okay, but the
but we all really agree that the problem is when there are
liens and therefore it's to protect the לקוחות. lekuchos, So version number
one is what are we protecting them from? An accident, that the
שטר shtar was written prior to the date the money was borrowed.
According to אביי, Abaye, no such thing, those accidents will never happen
because the liens will never exist as of the date they were
written. So according to אביי, Abaye, what are we protecting the לקוחות
lakochos. again? Against some scheme, that the שטר's shtar, already been paid
off, and we're protecting them against some scheme. By the way, at
least within the idea of פירעון וקנוניא, pirayon u'knunya, you can explain
it a little bit better why maybe there's like some rationale to
the fact that look, if the שטר shtar document was already paid
up, I'm going to be sloppier about the document, right? It's like
I tend to be, it's not a good מדה middah or whatever,
I tend to be sloppy about my receipts. Even though I know
I have to use my receipts to get reimbursed, you know, once
I put them in my wallet I forget about them, I'm sloppy.
So it's possible I paid my שטר, shtar I got it back.
If I'm being responsible, I tear it up. Or if we have
a scheme going, we get work on that scheme right away or
whatever. But you know, but the fact that I like this document
fell, if Michael had the money that I owed him ten thousand
dollars, it wouldn't have fallen from Michael. So therefore it's more likely
that it fell from me. So there already with this explanation that
it's a scheme and a paid-up document, you can understand a little
more rationale that the fact that it was found might be more
evidence that it really has been already paid up. Okay, so that's
the other explanation, the חייש לפירעון ולקנוניא. chaish le'pirayon u'le'knunya.
And how does that first רש״י Rashi that we looked at, that
in a way that's like that explanation,
but
it's much better according to this where it's already been paid up,
you can more understand being sloppy about it. Okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, ולשמואל דאמר לא חיישינן לפירעון וקנוניא, U'le'Shmuel
d'amar lo chaishinan le'pirayon u'knunya, שמואל Shmuel is going to say, we're
going to see this tomorrow, whatever, anyway that we're never afraid of
it. By the way, שמואל Shmuel goes so far to say we're
not afraid of it, that שמואל Shmuel says that if you find
a שטר shtar and the לוה loveh says I did not borrow
the money, you still give it to the מלוה, malveh, because we're
just never afraid that it's been paid up, and we're never afraid
whatever. I mean there'll be some limits to some of those cases,
but שמואל Shmuel really is saying like we always assume a שטר
shtar is legitimate and we don't assume that it's been paid, because
if it was paid it would be torn up, and if it's
not torn up it hasn't been paid, and therefore we're always going
to give it to the מלוה malveh no matter what the לוה
loveh says. Okay, so according to שמואל Shmuel דאמר לא חיישינן לפירעון
וקנוניא, d'amar lo chaishinan le'pirayon u'knunya, so מאי איכא למימר? mai ika
l'meimar? How do you explain in the משנה Mishnah why you don't
give it back? שמואל Shmuel is always ready to believe a שטר
shtar is legitimate and give it back. So אי ניחא אי סבר
לה כרב אסי Ei nicha ei savar lah k'Rav Assi דאמר בשטרי
הקנאה, d'amar b'shitrei hakna'ah, so if he says like רב אסי Rav
Assi that and limits his idea that we always give it back
or when we're not concerned about a predating to a case of
a שטר הקנאה, shtar hakna'ah, מוקי מתניתין בשטרי דלאו הקנאה. moki matnitin
b'shitrei d'lav hakna'ah. Then he would say in our משנה, Mishnah maybe
when שמואל Shmuel says you always give it back because it's a
שטר הקנאה, shtar hakna'ah, because a שטר הקנאה shtar hakna'ah maybe didn't
even matter if the money was borrowed, maybe a שטר הקנאה shtar
hakna'ah is automatically valid and so on. So a שטר הקנאה shtar
hakna'ah we're always going to give back. But a שטר shtar that's
not הקנאה, hakna'ah, there he's going to say, well one minute, maybe
that is a case of having been written in ניסן and the
money wasn't borrowed till תשרי. And even though he's not concerned for
פירעון pirayon and for קנוניא, knunya, maybe if it's not a שטר
הקנאה shtar hakna'ah he's concerned about a שטר shtar, that was written
prior to the money being lent. Okay, so maybe that's how he
would explain our משנה. Mishnah אלא אי סבר כאביי דאמר עדים בחתומינהו
זכיין לו, Ella ei savar k'Abaye d'amar eidim b'chasuminhu zachyan lo, but
the question is can you combine an אביי Abaye approach and a
שמואל Shmuel approach? אביי Abaye says עדים בחתומינהו זכיין לו, eidim b'chasuminhu
zachyan lo, so any שטר shtar when it's signed is immediately effective.
So therefore you cannot say don't give it back because it might
have been too early, it'll never be too early. So what are
you left with saying? Don't give it back because there might be
a scheme going on. But שמואל Shmuel says I'm never afraid about
a scheme, I think that if it was paid it would have
been torn up right away. So now you can't say the scheme,
you can't say too early, what explanation are you left with for
our משנה? mishnah Okay, אלא אי סבר כאביי דאמר עדים בחתומינהו זכיין
לו מאי איכא למימר? ella ei savar k'Abaye d'amar eidim b'chasuminhu zachyan
lo mai ika l'meimar? Is there any explanation of the משנה Mishnah
that could both work with אביי Abaye and שמואל Shmuel together? Both
say that it's effective as of the date of signing, and say
we're not afraid it's been paid and there's a scheme going. So
what is the concern? So the גמרא Gemara says שמואל מוקי למתניתין
כשאין חייב מודה. Shmuel moki l'matnitin k'she'ein chayav modeh. Yeah, the what
you would be according to that there's no way you could explain
the משנה Mishnah don't give it back if the לוה loveh agrees,
because there's nothing to be concerned about. It was effective as of
the date it was signed and we're not concerned of any scheme.
So why not give back? So you know what in the משנה
Mishnah. saying don't give it back? The case of the משנה Mishnah
of don't give it back is when the לוה loveh doesn't agree.
The לוה loveh. basically says I never borrowed the money, the document's
a forgery. Okay, that would be it can't be that he says
I paid, because אביי, Abaye, because שמואל Shmuel would say I don't
believe you that you paid, right, because then it would be torn
up. שמואל Shmuel says לא חיישינן לפירעון. lo chaishinan le'pirayon. But the
case in the משנה Mishnah where you wouldn't give it back is
when the לוה loveh, says don't give it back to him, I
never borrowed the money, it's a forgery. And even though normally we
don't believe claims of forgery by a document that's on the ground,
we are we are more suspect. Okay.
Yeah, so his motivation now rather than to protect לקוחות lakochos. is
to protect the לוה.
loveh Exactly.
So now there's a shift really. Exactly.
And then the question is if it's all to protect the לוה,
loveh why does the משנה Mishnah have to say whether there's אחריות
achrayus? or not אחריות? achrayus? Price so actually be irrelevant. The other
important question which leads to a big תוספות Tosafos on the עמוד
ב which is going to help us get through the דף today
is the question about if I'm saying it's a forgery and don't
give it back to him, I mean רש"י Rashi already deals with
this. So just get him to validate the signatures and that should
completely neutralize my claim. Fine, validate the signatures and then we'll give
it back to him. And the point might be that once it's
fallen on the ground it's so, and again this gets to this
idea of creating עדות edus out of something that right now is
not עדות, edus, we don't give it, we don't even give him
the opportunity to validate the signatures. You know sometimes people do such
good jobs of forgeries that they can get it validated even if
it is a forgery. Maybe. Now even of course we would never
say that because then you could never collect the document. Maybe in
this case it's being claimed to be a forgery, we're not going
to validate the signatures, we're just going to put it away, okay,
and that's what שמואל Shmuel is going to say. Of course the
question is going to be if that's the scenario, who cares about
אחריות? achrayus, You should just never give it back. What difference does
it make with or without אחריות? achrayus, So let's take a look.
שמואל מוקים לה למתניתין כשאין חייב מודה. Shmuel mukim lah l'matnisin k'she-ein
chayiv modeh. אי הכי, Ei hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara כי אין
בה אחריות נכסים אמאי יחזיר? ki ein bah achrayus nechasim amai yachazir?
Just because
there are no liens why do you give it
back? ניהי דלא גבי ממשועבדי מבני חורין מגבא
גבי. Nehei d'lo gabi mimshubadi mibnei chorin migba gabi. It'll collect from
the property that is unencumbered. It'll protect from me, from my מטלטלין.
metaltelin. So if I'm saying it's a forgery, why give it back?
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says:
שמואל לטעמיה. Shmuel l'taimei. שמואל Shmuel goes according to his reasoning דאמר
שמואל אמר רבי מאיר, d'amar Shmuel amar Rabbi Meir, רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir who would say that you don't give it back if there
is, if there is
אחריות, achrayus okay, אמר רבי מאיר שטר חוב שאין בו אחריות נכסים,
amar Rabbi Meir shtar chov she-ein bo achrayus nechasim, if you have
a debt document that's written that does not have liens written in
it, אין גובה לא ממשועבדים ולא מבני חורין. ein goveh lo mimshubadim
v'lo mibnei chorin.
Very strange idea, okay, if there's no liens written in, he basically
says it's an illegitimate document, okay, a שטר, shtar a debt document
without liens is not an acceptable debt document and it's basically worthless.
So
then
what's the point of giving
it
back?
וכי מאחר שאינו גובה אמאי יחזיר? V'ki me-acher she-eino goveh amai yachazir?
Why give it back to him? So אמר רבי נתן בר אושעיא
לצור פי
צלוחיתו של מילסף. amar Rabbi Natan bar Oshaya latzor pi tzluchiso shel
malsef. לצור פי צלוחיתו, Latzor pi tzluchiso, right, anyway, to use to
as a bottle
stopper.
Now
normally the גמרא Gemara uses this phrase ironically, it says, what, we're
talking about using it as a bottle stopper? But here we're saying
seriously, yeah, you know what, according to the רבנן Rabbanan it's whether
with or without, you know, it's always a legitimate document and therefore
never give it back. I'm saying I didn't borrow the money so
don't give it back to him with or without אחריות, achrayus it's
a legitimate document, he'll use it against me. But רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says if there's no אחריות achrayus, it's a worthless document, so
you can give it to him, not that he could ever use
it, but he'll use it as a piece of paper, he'll use
it as a bottle stopper. So the גמרא Gemara says: ונהדרוהו ללוה
ולצור פי צלוחיתא דלוה? v'nehadruhu l'loveh v'latzor pi tzluchisa d'loveh? Okay,
so if that's now what the משנה Mishnah is about, who gets
to use it as a bottle stopper? I mean the רבנן Rabbanan
say it's more than a bottle stopper, that's why the רבנן Rabbanan
say don't return it. But if רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says return
it as a bottle stopper, why you giving it to the מלווה?
Give it to me, I want it as a bottle stopper. So
the גמרא Gemara says: לוה הוא דאמר לא היו דברים מעולם. loveh
hu d'amar lo hayu devarim me-olam. No, because I'm saying it's a
forgery. So of course I don't get it, okay, so I'm denying
it ever existed. So of course he claims it is, let him
take it as a bottle stopper. Okay, anyway, so that's version 2.
So this version started as we're going to start by assuming the
לוה loveh agrees, the problem is the liens, so where are the
problems? The problems are maybe it was written before the liens existed,
right, maybe it was written before the money was borrowed, or
maybe there's a scheme going on. If you shut off the opportunity
of either of those explanations, you take שמואל Shmuel who doesn't believe
in schemes and a שטר shtar being paid, and you take אביי
Abaye who believes that the liens always exist from the date of
being signed, then you have to shift gears and say the case
is a case of I don't agree that I borrowed the money
and the concern is not protecting the לקוחות, lakochos? it's protecting me.
So now we're going to do that from that perspective. We're going
to sort of just sort of shift our orientation. As opposed to
starting by talking about the לוה loveh does
agree, we're now going to start by talking about the case that
the לוה loveh. doesn't agree. אמר רבי אלעזר. Amar Rabbi Elazar. So
now it's going to be a little bit repeating. Said רבי אלעזר:
Rabbi Elazar: מחלוקת בשאין חייב מודה. machlokes b'she-ein chayiv modeh. The whole
debate is when the לוה loaveh doesn't agree, right, what we just
sort of ended the previous discussion with, okay, and it's about protecting
the לוה. loaveh רבי מאיר סבר שטר שאין בו אחריות נכסים אינו
גובה לא ממשועבדים ולא מבני חורין. Rabbi Meir savar shtar she-ein bo
achrayus nechasim eino goveh lo mimshubadim v'lo mibnei chorin. So similar to
what we said before, right, or the same, that רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says a שטר shtar. without אחריות achrayus is worthless and that's
why you're allowed to return it because it's really worthless.
רבנן סברי מגבא גבי, Rabbanan savri migba gavi, it is not worthless,
it can be used to collect. And therefore they say never return
it. The לוה loaveh, doesn’t agree. If the לוה loaveh doesn’t agree,
you cannot return it to protect the לוה, loaveh forget about the
לקוחות. lakochos, אבל כשחייב מודה, Aval keshehachayav modeh, if the לוה loaveh
does agree, דברי הכל יחזיר. divrei hakol yachzir. In that case, okay,
now it’s clarifying the flip. If you start by framing the משנה
Mishnah that the לוה loaveh doesn’t agree, what would be the case
when the לוה loaveh does agree? So in that case, everybody would
say you give it back and you’re not concerned for protecting the
לקוחות. lakochos. Why are you not concerned for protecting
לקוחות? lakochos, ולא חיישינן לפרעון ולקנוניא V’lo chaishinan lipir'on u'l'kanyia because even
if there are liens, we’re not concerned about schemes and about it
being paid off, presumably we’re also not concerned about it money having
been bought, the שטר shtar being written before the money was borrowed.
So this is taking it from the other perspective. All those concerns,
those are non-concerns.
We’re not concerned that it will be written before the money was
borrowed or maybe פסק לאגבאי וכתבו לזכות לו. pasak l'agba'i vechaso lizechos
lo. We’re not concerned about schemes. So if the לוה loaveh. agrees,
there’s nobody to protect. We don’t have to protect the לקוחות, lakochos.
everything is on the up-and-up, give it back. And the only case
in the משנה Mishnah that’s being debated is the לוה loaveh. doesn’t
agree and we’re out to protect the לוה. loaveh. Yes, Joe.
How can you collect from בני חורין? benei chorin?
What do you mean? It’s my property, it’s not something that’s purchased.
בני חורין Benei chorin means property that still is in the possession
of the לוה.
loaveh
Yes, right, but in other words, mean property, משעבדי, mishabadi, right?
You can collect from mean property.
Pardon me? Yeah, you can collect from mean property.
Not if there’s no אחריות achrayus נכסים in the שטר. shtar.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is saying if there’s no אחריות, achrayus, not
only do you not have liens, you can’t even use the שטר
shtar at all.
I understand that. Is there any... how can you normally collect from
non-lien property? You can’t, right?
From the person, from the borrower himself.
You can’t collect from other people.
The borrower
can only pay in cash.
But that’s always the case, in other words, if it’s liened property,
you’re taking from the לוה.
loaveh No, when you come to me and you come and you
get my take my car or you take the money out of
my wallet, that’s not a lien. That’s just because I owe you
the money and that’s the money I have on me. Liens means
something that will stick with the property even after it changes hands.
Right, okay.
Yeah, I understand that. So for רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, to me
it’s the difference if there’s אחריות achrayus? or not, but if we
say that the לוה loaveh is not admitting and it’s on the
ground, which is a ריעותא, re'uta, right? Why do we care if
there’s אחריות achrayus. or not?
What
for?
Because if there’s no אחריות, achrayus then it’s a worthless document.
And if there is אחריות?
achrayut, Then it’s not worthless.
Why not? I mean, I’m disagreeing and it’s on the ground.
That’s why we don’t return it if it has אחריות.
achrayut, No, but I’m saying why do we say that even if
it has אחריות achrayut it’s worthless because A, I’m disagreeing and B,
now it’s on the ground.
What?
It’s not worthless had the מלוה malveh gotten it back, it would
be a very powerful document, and that’s why we don’t return it
when I don’t agree.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says if the מלוה malveh has it without
the אחריות, it’s still worthless, so you might as well give it
back to him. But if it has אחריות, it’s going to be
very powerful. So if the לוה loaveh doesn’t agree, don’t give it
to the מלוה. malveh. All right, so the גמרא Gemara, says like
this: רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, now רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says מחלוקת כשחייב מודה. machlokas keshehachayav modeh. No, no, no. So this
now, what we had sort of started the סוגיא, sugya, now it’s
a debate of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, how
to read the משנה. Mishnah רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says the משנה
Mishnah is when the לוה loaveh does agree. רבי מאיר סבר שטר
שאין בו אחריות נכסים ממשעבדי הוא דלא גבי אבל מבני חורין גבי
גבי. Rabbi Meir sabar shtar she’ein bo achrayut nechasim mishabadi hu d’lo
gavi aval mibnei chorin gavi gavi. That רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
if it doesn’t have liens, it’s still used to collect. You can
still use it. It’s still a good שטר. shtar You just don’t
collect from property the לוה loaveh. has. You just can’t collect from
other people. Okay, and therefore, if the לוה loaveh agrees, you might
as well give it back to the מלוה malveh because the only
person going to be affected by a שטר shtar is the לוה.
loaveh ורבנן סברי, Verabbanan savri, and the Rabbis hold, and this is
what was implicit before, ממשעבדי נמי גבי. mi’mishabadi nami gavi. No, even
without liens written in, there are always liens in a loan document.
And therefore, even if the לוה loaveh agrees, don’t give it back
because we have to protect the לקוחות. lakochot. Okay, so that’s what
we’ve been assuming until now, that the לוה loaveh agrees, we’re protecting
the לקוחות, lakochot. and the debate in the משנה Mishnah is do
liens exist even if they’re not written in. אבל כשאין חייב מודה,
Aval keshe’ein chayav modeh,
but if the לוה loaveh doesn’t agree, in that case, דברי הכל
לא יחזיר, divrei hakol lo yachzir, of course don’t give it back.
Okay, because the document, everybody would agree that the document at least
is valid to collect from the לוה loaveh and if he’s not
agreeing, why should you give it back to the מלוה? malveh? דחיישינן
לפרעון. De-chaishinan lipir'on.
Now, חיישינן לפרעון chaishinan lipir'on
is actually more the explanation of why not to... why we have
to protect the לקוחות. lakochot. Even if the לוה loaveh agrees, you
don’t necessarily give it back if there are liens because there might...
it might have been paid and there might be a scheme going
on. Okay, so we’re just recapping. All right, one read of the
משנה Mishnah is the לוה loveh doesn’t agree. If the לוה loveh
doesn’t agree, the only explanation of why רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would
allow it to be given back is he says the שטר shtar
is worthless. Okay. So we're just recapping, alright? One read of the
משנה Mishnah is the לוה loveh doesn't agree. If the לוה loveh
doesn't agree, the only explanation of why רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would
allow it to be given back is he says the שטר shtar
is worthless. Okay? And but anytime the שטר shtar is not worthless,
don't give it back if the לוה loveh. doesn't agree. The other
explanation is no. If the לוה loveh doesn't agree, then you would
never give back the שטר shtar because the שטר shtar could always
be used against the לוה. loveh The only case is that the
לוה loveh does agree, and then the question is, are there liens?
And if there are liens, we have to protect the לקוחות. lakochot.
What are we protecting them against? That the שטר shtar has been
paid off and there is some scheme going on. Yes, Jenna?
Just want to hear what you're saying. This חישינן לקנוניא, chashinan l'knunya,
we're saying this is when a לוה loveh doesn't agree, so we're
worried that he paid it already?
No, so that's why I said the חישינן לקנוניא chashinan l'knunya is
really more explaining that's why we don't give it back even when
he does agree and there are liens. That it really is explaining
the first half of the phrase, not the second. Okay. All right.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Where are we? Okay. תניא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן ותיופתא דרבי אלעזר בחדא
ותיופתא דשמואל
בתרתי. Tanya k'vatei d'Rabbi Yochanan u'tiyuvta d'Rabbi Elazar b'chada u'tiyuvta d'Shmuel b'tarti.
So we have a ברייתא Baraisa explicitly like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
that the debate is that the לוה loveh, agrees and it's a
concern about scheming, and it contradicts רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar in one
way and שמואל Shmuel in two ways because שמואל Shmuel and רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar are the ones that say that the date is
when the לוה loveh doesn't agree,
when the לוה, loveh excuse me, does not agree. Okay, let's take
a look. What's the ברייתא? Baraisa? מצא
שטרי חוב, Matza shitrei chov, you found documents of debt, שיש בהן
אחריות נכסים, sheyesh bahen achrayut nechasim, and they have liens. אף על
פי ששניהם מודים, Af al pi she'shneihem modim, you cannot get a
more explicit ברייתא Baraisa than this, both parties agree, לא יחזיר לא
לזה ולא לזה, lo yachzir lo l'zeh v'lo l'zeh, don't give it
back to either. I.e. don't give it to the לוה loveh because
the מלוה malveh says it's still valid, but don't give it back
to the מלוה malveh because there are liens and you have to
protect the לקוחות. lakochot Okay? So what are you protecting them from?
Presumably you're protecting them from a case that was paid and there's
some scheme going on. So that's explicitly like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
that even if it's agreed, if there are liens, don't give it
back. אין בהן אחריות נכסים, the only debate is if there are
no liens, whether the liens are implicit. Okay? If there are no
liens written in, בזמן שהלוה מודה, bizman she'ha'loveh modeh, יחזיר למלוה. yachzir
l'malveh. אין הלוה מודה, Ein ha'loveh modeh, לא יחזיר לא לזה ולא
לזה, lo yachzir lo l'zeh v'lo l'zeh, דברי רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir
So then if the לוה loveh agrees, give it back, but if
he doesn't agree, don't give it back. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says if there are no
liens, there are no liens. שהיה רבי מאיר אומר, She'hayah Rabbi Meir
omer, שטר שיש בו אחריות נכסים, shtar she'yesh bo achrayut nechasim, גובה
מנכסים משועבדים. goveh mi'nechasim m'shubadim. If the liens are written in, then
you can collect from encumbered property. ושאין בו אחריות נכסים, V'she'ein bo
achrayut nechasim, גובה מנכסים בני חורין. goveh mi'nechasim bnei chorin. But if
the liens are not written in, you don't have liens. Okay? So
everybody agrees, don't give it back even if, that the case of
the משנה Mishnah, is the לוה loveh agrees, don't give it back
if there are liens because you've got to protect the לקוחות. lakochot.
And the whole debate is, are there liens when it's not explicitly
written in the document? וחכמים אומרים, and the חכמים say, אחד זה
ואחד זה, echad zeh v'echad zeh, whether it has the liens written
in or not, גובה מנכסים משועבדים. goveh mi'nechasim m'shubadim. The שטר shtar
can be used to collect from encumbered property, and therefore never give
back a שטר shtar even if the לוה loveh agrees because you
will be endangering the לקוחות. lakochot. Okay? So this is a straight
proof that the case of our משנה Mishnah, with this ברייתא Baraisa
is what our משנה Mishnah is talking about. That the case of
our משנה is that the לוה loveh agrees, the concern is the
presence of liens and to protect the לקוחות lakochot. because maybe there
is some scheme going on. תיובתא דרבי אלעזר בחדא. Tiyuvta d'Rabbi Elazar
b'chada. Now that contradicts רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar in one way. What
does it contradict him? דאמר רבי אלעזר, D'amar Rabbi Elazar, דאמר d'amar
excuse me, רבי אלעזר אמר Rabbi Elazar amar לרבי מאיר, l'Rabbi Meir,
שטר שאין בו אחריות נכסים, shtar she'ein bo achrayut nechasim, אינו גובה
מנכסים משועבדים ולא מנכסים בני חורין. eino goveh mi'nechasim m'shubadim v'lo mi'nechasim
bnei chorin.
He said that the reason you would return it for רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir is because without אחריות it's completely worthless. Okay? And here
we saw that no, that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. says it's good,
it just doesn't have liens. וקאמר בין לרבי מאיר בין לרבנן חיישינן
לקנוניא. V'ka'amar bein l'Rabbi Meir bein l'Rabbanan chashinan l'knunya. And he also
said, that's the two points which the גמרא Gemara is going to
point out, that we're never concerned about a scheme going on. And
this ברייתא Baraisa teaches against both of these. וברייתא קתני, U'baraisa katani,
number one, שטר שאין בו אחריות נכסים, shtar she'ein bo achrayut nechasim,
משעבדי הוא דלא גבי, m'shabdei hu d'lo gabi, בני חורין מיהא גבי.
bnei chorin miha gabi. Number one, without liens, it's still a legitimate
document, you just can't use it to collect from encumbered property, and
therefore the whole issue is protecting the לקוחות. lakochot. וקתני בין לרבי
מאיר בין לרבנן חיישינן לקנוניא. V'katani bein l'Rabbi Meir bein l'Rabbanan chashinan
l'knunya.
And therefore, and point number two is that the concern is that
we are concerned that there's some scheme and that's why we don't
return it if the guy admits. If the guy admits, it's a
legitimate שטר shtar and there are liens, and therefore don't return it,
you know, if there are liens don't return it to protect the
לקוחות. lakuchos, So the גמרא says, לחייש לקנוניא. l'chayesh l'knunya. דקתני אף
על פי ששניהם מודים, D'katani af al pi she'shneihem modim, even if
they both agree, לא יחזיר לא לזה ולא לזה, lo yachzir lo
l'zeh v'lo l'zeh, don't give it back. Why should you not give
it back if they both agree? אמר חיישינן לקנוניא. Amar chashinan l'knunya.
So you see this totally proves רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan point. It
proves רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan point that number one, that the שטר
shtar is still legitimate according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir רבי מאיר
says it can be used, it just can't be used for לקוחות.
lakuchos. So if the שטר shtar is legitimate, the only reason you
would return it is because the לוה loveh agrees. And therefore the
only concern is to protect the לקוחות. lakuchos which means we are
concerned about schemes. So the גמרא, anyway, this totally contradicts ר' אלעזר,
Rebbi Elazar, which says the exact opposite of that, that we're not
concerned about schemes, the only reason you return it is because the
שטר is worthless and the לוה isn't agreeing etc. So the גמרא
says הני תרתי הוא, hahani tarti hu, so those are two ways
you contradicted ר' אלעזר. Rebbi Elazar. Number one, you contradicted ר' אלעזר's
Rebbi Elazar statement, he says a שטר is worthless and we said
it's legitimate, it just doesn't have liens. And number two, ר' אלעזר
Rebbi Elazar says we're not concerned about schemes, and here we see
we are concerned about schemes. So the גמרא says חדא היא, chada
hu, yeah, but it's all one thing, דחד טעמא
הוא, dechada ta'ama hu, the reason, his two positions are one led
to the other, דמשום דאמר ר' אלעזר demishum de'amar Rebbi Elazar מחלוקת
בשאין חייב מודה, machlokes beshein chayav modeh,
since he said the debate was that the guy, the issue in
the משנה was that the guy didn't admit to the loan, so
הוא מתרץ הכי, hu metaretz hachi, so that's why he had to
explain, oh, so wait a minute, if he doesn't admit to the
loan then why would you ever return the document according to ר'
מאיר? Rebbi Meir? Oh, it's because ר' מאיר Rebbi Meir will say
the document is worthless. So by saying the debate in the משנה
is, I mean we went through it a little quickly but I
think you guys got the general sense, by saying the debate in
the משנה is when the לוה doesn't admit and even there ר'
מאיר Rebbi Meir would say give back the document, the only way
you could explain that is by asserting that according to ר' מאיר
Rebbi Meir the document is totally worthless. So those two assertions are
like are intertwined. Okay, but so we real we contradicted both points
but they're intertwined points. And we have shown that this ברייתא braisa
makes it very clear what should definitely be פשט pshat in the
משנה, that the issue is the presence or the absence of liens.
If that's the issue, the concern is protecting the לקוחות, and therefore
if the guy, if even if the guy admits, we're not going
to give back the document with liens because of the there might
be a scheme against the לקוחות. And the whole debate in the
משנה, we'll get to that tomorrow, the whole debate in the משנה
is whether there are liens even when they're not written there. Okay,
but whenever there are liens, we are not going to give it
back because we have to protect the possible לקוחות who are being
schemed against and who are being taken advantage of. All right, to
be continued.